A Finding Aid to the Molly Saltman "Art and Artists" Interviews, 1966-1967, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Molly Saltman "Art and Artists" interviews
1966-1967
Archives of American Art
Saltman, Molly, 1915-2010
AAA.saltmoll
Archival Resource Key
2.4 Linear feet
The Molly Saltman "Art and Artists" interviews measure 2.4 linear feet and contain 62 sound recording interviews and lectures with art collectors, teachers, actors, and artists. The interviews were conducted by Molly Saltman from 1966-1967 as part of the "Art and Artists" radio series broadcast on the KPAL radio station in Palm Springs, California. Additional recordings of KPAL content and nonbroadcast content were discovered upon digitization, including a Los Angeles Art Association anniversary event and a Charles White slide lecture.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Molly Saltman in 1986.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center.
Biographical / Historical
The Molly Saltman "Art and Artists" radio program was broadcast on KPAL radio station in Palm Springs, California from November 2, 1966 to March 4, 1967 on Mondays and Wednesdays at 10:30AM. Molly Saltman (1915-2010), the producer and interviewer for this broadcast, was a well-known Palm Springs artist during this time. Specializing in abstract watercolors, her work was featured in a number of local art shows as well as exhibited in the Los Angeles County Museum of Art, the Palm Springs Desert Museum, and the Hartfield Gallery in Los Angeles. She was also closely involved with the Desert Mental Health Association and served as Chairwoman of the Jewish Family Service in Palm Springs, California.
Scope and Contents
The Molly Saltman "Art and Artists" interviews measure 2.4 linear feet and contain 62 sound recording interviews and lectures with art collectors, teachers, actors, and artists. The interviews were conducted by Molly Saltman from 1966-1967 as part of the "Art and Artists" radio series broadcast on the KPAL radio station in Palm Springs, California. Additional recordings of KPAL content and nonbroadcast content were discovered upon digitization, including a Los Angeles Art Association anniversary event and a Charles White slide lecture.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the sound recordings are arranged as one series.
Series 1: Interviews and other recordings, circa 1963-1968 (Box 1-3, 2.4 linear feet)
Existence and Location of Copies
All of the sound recordings in this collection have been copied for research access and digital copies are available in the Archives of American Art offices.
Other Finding Aids
A list of interviewees is available in all Archives of American Art offices.
Actors; Art, American; Art--Collectors and collecting--Interviews; Art teachers -- Interviews; Artists -- Interviews; Interviews; Lectures; Sound recordings; Falkenstein, Claire, 1908-1997; Feitelson, Lorser, 1898-1978; Hamilton, Richard, 1922-; Hopper, Dennis, 1936-; Levine, Jack, 1915-2010; Lytton, Bart, 1912-1969; Macdonald-Wright, Stanton, 1890-1973; Natzler, Gertrud; Natzler, Otto; Nyiri, Joseph, 1937-; Partch, Harry, 1901-1974; Price, Vincent, 1911-1993; Secunda, Arthur; Wayne, June, 1918-2011; White, Charles (1918-1979); Art and artists (Radio program)
- Interviews and Other Recordings, circa 1963-1968; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 2.4 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains 62 interviews (only one transcribed) conducted as part of the "Art and Artists" radio broadcast series by Molly Saltman between 1966 and 1967, each approximately 20 minutes long. The interviewees include art collector Bart Lytton, teachers, such as Lorser Feitelson and Arthur Secunda, actors Vincent Price and Dennis Hopper, composer Harry Partch, and a wide-variety of artists, including Claire Falkenstein, Richard Hamilton, Jack Levine, Stanton MacDonald-Wright, Joseph Nyiri, Otto and Gertrude Natzler, June Wayne, and Charles White.
  Also found in this series are other events and programs on subjects related to the contemporary art world of Southern California, and other Palm Springs local programs, which may be present due to the practice of recycling audio tape. These include an additional lecture by Edward Biberman, a slide lecture by Charles White, a Los Angeles Art Association anniversary event, a lecture an performance by composer Henri Tamianka, and a lecture by an unknown speaker on the topic of Early Western Artists. Additional local programs found include a candidate forum, a weekly report by local congressman John Tunney, and a teen program broadcast on KPAL.
  Unless otherwise indicated, the content listed below consists of interviews.
  Arrangement
  The "Art and Artists" interviews are arranged alphabetically by interviewee's last name. Programs found in addition to the "Art and Artists" series are listed in logical order by name or subject; note that these additional programs typically share tapes with other content.
  - Ralph Altman, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 1)
  - Edward Biberman Art History Lecture, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 2)
  - Edward Biberman Interview, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 34)
  - Nicholas Brigante, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 3)
  - Katherine Brugger, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 4)
  - Walter Carlson, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 5)
  - Edmund Carpenter, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 6)
  - Lynn Cordner, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 7)
  - Ken Donahue, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 8)
  - Lecture, "Early Western Artist", 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 9)
    This lecture takes place at the Joslyn Museum and is by an unknown speaker on the subject of Early Western Artists
  - Leonard Edmundson, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 10)
  - Edith Ekros, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 11)
  - Claire Falkenstein, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 12)
  - Lorser Feitelson, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 13)
  - Max Finkelstein, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 14)
  - James Gill, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 15)
  - Gerald Gladstone, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 16)
  - Richard Hamilton, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel; 1 Sound cassette (Box 1, Item 17)
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Sound cassette is an access copy
  - Mrs. Dalzell Hatfield, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 18)
  - Henry Hopkins and Maurice Tuchman, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 19)
  - Dennis Hopper, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 3 Sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 20)
  - Ben Horowitz, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 21)
  - Mahender K. Jain and Ravi K. Jain, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 22)
  - James Kelly, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 23)
  - Abbot Kaplan, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 24)
  - Fred Katz, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 25)
  - Roger Kuntz, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 26)
  - Felix Landau, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 27)
  - Jules Langsner, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 28)
  - Jack Levine, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 1, Item 29)
  - Lawrence Lipton, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 1)
  - Stephen Longstreet, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 5 Sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 2)
  - Bart Lytton, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 3)
  - Stanton MacDonald-Wright, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 3 Sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 4)
  - Ed Marin, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Item 27)
    Found on tape with Carpenter interview (reel 1, side 2)
  - Robert Marko, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 5)
  - Paul Maure and Andre Karlson, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 6)
  - Otto and Gertrude Natzler, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 7)
  - Joseph Nyiri, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 8)
  - Harry Partch, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 9)
  - Lily Pons, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 10)
  - Vincent Price, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 11)
  - Ernest Raboff, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 12)
  - Fanya Chocam Sage, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 13)
  - Atzie Schiff, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 14)
  - Arthur Secunda, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 15)
  - Art Seidenbaum, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 16)
  - Austin Sellery, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 17)
  - Vicci Sperry, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 18)
  - Gloria Stuart, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 19)
  - Henri Temianka, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 20)
  - Henri Temianka lecture and performance, circa 1965-1968; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 27)
  - Harry Trimborn, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 21)
  - Maurice Tuchman, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 22)
  - Congressman John Tunney weekly radio report, circa 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Item 10)
    Found on side 2 of tape with Charles White lecture.
  - Ken Tyler, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 23)
  - Gordon Wagner, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 2, Item 24)
  - Gordon Wagner and Arthur Secunda, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 3 Sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 25)
  - June Wayne, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 3 Sound tape reels (Box 2, Item 26)
  - Al Wein, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 3, Item 1)
  - Frederick Whitaker and Eileen Monoghan, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel Includes transcript; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 2)
  - Charles White, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 3, Item 3)
  - Charles White slide lecture, circa 1965-1968; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 3, Item 11)
  - Charles White and Ben Horowitz, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 3, Item 4)
  - Charles White and Ben Horowitz, Broadcast version, circa 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 3, Item 12)
    Broadcast version includes programming announcements and introductory material not present in original recording (Box 3, item 4).
  - Helen Wurdeman, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound tape reels (Box 3, Item 5)
  - Peter Yates, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 3, Item 6)
  - Colin Young, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 3, Item 7)
  - Joseph Young, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 3, Item 8)
  - Father Jerry Ziegengeist, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 3, Item 9)
  - Los Angeles Art Association anniversary event, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Item 32)
    Speakers include Helen Wurdeman, Nick Brigante, Peter Krasnow, and Lorser Feitelson, among others, recounting stories in the history of the association for an anniversary event. Recording is fragmentary and shares tape with multiple programs, including Gill (reel 2, side 2), Kaplan (reel 1, side 2), Partch (reel 1, side 2), and Raboff (reel 1, side 2).
  - Interview with braille music notation expert, circa 1965-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Item 28)
    Found on side 2 of tape with Maure interview.
  - Teen program on KPAL radio, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Item 30)
    Found on tapes with Feitelson interview.
  - Local candidate forum, Palm Springs, circa 1965-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Item 31)
    Found on same tape as reel 2 of Hatfield program.